SHIJIL P

Software Engineer (Java)
shijil612@gmail.com +91 7025798225
https://www.linkedin.com/in/shijil-purushothaman-java-developer
Pazhayaveedu Malappattam kannur Kerala 670631

An experienced software engineer(Java) with 3.5 years of relevant experience. Have a passion for developing innovative programs that expedite the efficiency and effectiveness of organizational success. Well-versed in technology and writing code to create systems that are reliable and user-friendly. Confident communicator, strategic thinker, and innovative creator to develop software that is customized to meet a company's organizational needs, highlight its core competencies, and further its success.

KEY COMPETENCIES

Software Development Web Development Agile methodology Version Control Problem Solving
Algorithm and Data Structures
Software Architecture
Testing and Quality Assurance

Team leadership Communication Operations management Security Awareness

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

TATA Consultancy Service Asst.System Engineer

APR 2022 - Present

- Developed a REST API that enabled integration with third-party services.
- Collaborated with other developers to ensure shared code was of high quality and met design specifications
- Developed unit tests to ensure code quality and ensure compliance with software development best practices
- Designed and implemented a secure authentication system that used for user authorization and authentication
- · Optimized code for performance and scalability, resulting in decrease in response time for end users
- Implemented an automated deployment process that reduced time-to-deployment from several days to several hours
- Designed and implemented a caching system that improved system performance and response times.
- Implemented a caching system using Redis that improved application performance.
- Implemented a secure authentication system that ensured user data was protected and met industry compliance standards.
- Working on agile scrum methodology and involving in stand-up meetings to monitor the progress.
- Implementing the backend business layers using spring and web services. Handling git and push and maintain code in the repository.
- Handling code deployment using Jenkin in test environment and production environment.
- Implementing Java EE components using Spring MVC, Spring IOC, Spring Transactions, and Spring Security Modules.
- Developing application using Java Spring Boot, Hibernate, Restful services with good quality of code.
- Configuring the spring integration XML to route request to respective databases.
- Involving in the complete software development life cycle including requirement analysis, design, implementation, testing, and maintenance.
- Actively involved in the analysis, detail design, development, bug fixing and enhancement in agile methodology.
- Participating in scrum meetings as part of iteration development process.
- Delivering the new and complex high-quality solutions to clients in response to varying business requirements.

Claysys Technologies Software Engineer

- Developed REST APIs and implemented authentication protocols, such as OAuth, to securely expose data to clients
- Developed and maintained software in multiple programming languages, such as Java, Python, and JavaScript
- Designed and developed a scalable, high-availability web application that handled concurrent users with minimal downtime
- Created a Continuous Integration/Continuous Deployment (CI/CD) pipeline that reduced time-todeployment.
- · Led a team of developers to successfully complete a major software project on time and within budget
- Conducted code reviews and mentored junior developers to improve code quality and ensure adherence to best practices
- Extensive Object-Oriented Development OOP/OOD experience.
- Good working knowledge of application development and maintenance life cycle process.
- Projects: Behavioral-insights This Java application extracts data from ARCU and exports it to CSV files
- Repgen-Symitar-PowerOn Episys core system to third-party products and the ancillary applications developed internally by the credit union

Pythos Hub NOV 2020 - Feb 2021

Junior Developer

- · Key Responsibilities/ Achievements
- Developed full-stack web applications which processed, analyzed, and rendered data visually.
- Liaised with back-end developers, front-end developers, quality assurance testers, and CTO as needed.
- Managed time-sensitive updates, including content changes and database upgrades.
- Planned, wrote, and debugged web applications and software with complete accuracy

EDUCATION

Bachelor of Technology (B. Tech) degree 2015 - 2019

Computer Science and Engineering MES College of Engineering Malapuram APJ Abdul Kalam Technological University

SKILLS AND PROFICIENCIES

- Full Stack Development
- JAVA (Spring boot, Spring, Hibernate, Jsp, Servle)
- MySQL
- Oracle PSQL
- ReactJS
- · HTML, CSS, Bootstrap

TOOLS

- Intellij IDE
- Maven
- Git
- Jenkins
- Docker
- · Products Microsoft

COURSES AND ACHIEVEMENTS

- Completion Certificate Java and Python (ABC Technology Training & Upskilling Bangalore)
- Full Stack Developer Course (ICT Academy of Kerala)
- · Version Control with Git
- · Full stack-Angular and Java spring boot
- Got On The Spot Award and On The Spot(Team) Award
- Led a team of developers to deliver a critical software project
- Implemented an automated testing framework that reduced software defects and improved overall product quality.
- Developed and deployed a system optimization plan that reduced server response time